# Numan Arif Senior Android Developer - Plume Design, Inc.(USA)

numanarif19@gmail.com / +923127253072

https://www.linkedin.com/in/numanarif/ / https://qithub.com/NumanArif / https://numanarif.qithub.io

### **Summary**

I am an Android mobile application developer with about 6 years of experience, having a strong background in creating complex mobile applications using **Kotlin & Java**. I make it my goal to create apps with the user perspective in mind and have in-depth knowledge of industry practices and application development protocols while understanding the value of clean, structured, testable, scalable, and maintainable code by following the best programming principles and guidelines.

I am eager to learn new technologies and look for ways to better myself in this rapidly changing industry.

#### **Technical Skills**

- ✓ Programming Languages: Kotlin, Kotlin Multi Mobile, Java SE, XML, SQL
- ✓ General: DataBinding in AndrFrodoClean Architecture, Repository structure, MVVM, MVP, SOLID, REST/JSON, GraphQL with Apollo Android Client
- ✓ Frameworks: Android Mobile SDK, .NET
- ✓ Reactive Programing: RXJava/Kotlin, Kotlin Coroutines, FLOW
- ✓ Databases: Room, SQLite
- ✓ Android Specific: Hilt, Dagger2, Retrofit, OKHttp, AndroidX, Android Architecture Components, Navigation Component, DataStore, Android Motion Layout, viewpager2, EventBus, Android Plot (Graphing Library), GSON, GoogleMaps, GoogleMaps Utils SDK, GooglePlaces API, Firebase (Analytics, Crashlytics, Remote Configs, Firebase A/B Testing, R8 obfuscation, Multi Modular Android Apps
- ✓ Tools: Android Studio, NetBeans
- ✓ UI/UX Tools: Figma, Zeplin, AdobeXD
- ✓ Payment Gateways: Payfort, HyperPay
- ✓ Testing: Unit Testing using Mockito
- ✓ SVC/SVC Tools: Git, Bitbucket, Github
- ✓ CI/CD: Bitrise, CircleCI, App Center
- ✓ Development Methodologies: Agile, Scrum
- ✓ Analytic Platforms: OneSignal, App Virality

### **Work Experience**

### **Turing**

July 2020 – Present Senior Android Developer

Plume Design, Inc(Remote Job - USA)
July 2020 - Present

### **Projects**

**Frodo:** Frodo is a code name for a fitness tracker application through a smart ring which is available for both iOS & Android. I am working in a team to develop this project which is covering a large number of fitness activities for personal wellbeing e.g Live Fitness Activity Tracking, Daily Activity Summary for a user, Fitness Activity histograms, Heart Rate, Sleep, Stress monitoring, and many more.

Being an android developer my duties include code reviews, estimating and planning tasks, maintaining, and developing new features by following best android practices and Clean architecture.

### **Technologies:**

MVVM, Kotlin, Kotlin Multi Mobile, Kotlin Coroutines, Kotlin Flow, REST, Firebase remote configs, Firebase A/B Testing, Github, Android Plot, Clean Architecture with repository structure, Jetpack Navigation, Dagger-Hilt

### **BarqApp**

November 2019 – June 2020 Senior Android Developer

## **Projects**

- ✓ Barq Consumer: An android application for users to order anything they want from their nearby stores and shops in three simple steps.
  - Select a delivery address
  - Add required items to list and place order
  - Pay online once the order is picked and the invoice is uploaded

The consumer app has a very user-friendly interface with dual language support and live order tracking functionality.

https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.kaakati.barqconsumer&hl=en

✓ BarqApp V2: is a unique concept (purely developed in Kotlin) that enables users to send/carry packages in cities/countries. The user just need to do is to create a package using the mobile application, by providing the pickup and dropoff locations and then that package is listed on google maps from where a traveler, who has created a trip through this platform can request the sender to carry the package and drop the package on the destination.

# Technologies:

Kotlin, Kotlin Coroutines, GraphQL, Android DataBinding, Firebase remote configs, HyperPay Payment SDK, EventBus, Google Maps SDKs, Help Crunch SDK for live chat, and support.

### **Blue Pace Apps**

Feb 2019 – October 2019 Android Developer

### **Projects**

Swyft Delivery: Anything anywhere, is the slogan of the Swyft Delivery app. By using this platform users can order their favorite food and will receive it on their doorsteps. All they have to do is select items then enter a pickup and destination location. Once the items are at their doorstep, users can pay cash to the driver or can pay online.

### Technologies:

Kotlin, Java SE, Google Maps, Google Places API, Dagger2, Retrofit, Firebase remote configs, Payfort Payment SDK, ButterKnife, Deep Linking, Zendesk, Braze, Sendbird,

### Shahi Sawari

April 2016 – Jan 2019 Android Developer

## **Projects**

- ✓ Shahi Sawari: Shahi Sawari monthly pick and drop services are designed for daily commute to and from school, college, and workplace while keeping convenience, safety, and affordability in mind. Using the app one can Track their trip on the mobile app and can share live location with loved ones for added safety. Book for a month and forget the hassle of daily bookings. Get picked up from your doorstep and drop back at the same time daily. <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=shahisawari.pk">https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=shahisawari.pk</a>
- ✓ Shahi Sawari Driver: An android application that enables a TukTuk driver to be a part of the digital rikshaw pooling system to get requests. This app comes with many hidden features to alert drivers if they have not started the ride and move away from a pickup point and also monitor the traveling speed.

### Technologies:

Java SE, Dagger2, Retrofit, Android Overlays, OneSignal, App Virality

# **Education**

Bachelor's Degree in Information Technology 2011 – 2015 University of Gujrat, Pakistan